<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://rishabkdoshi.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://rishabkdoshi.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en" /><updated>2018-09-04T17:10:47+05:30</updated><id>https://rishabkdoshi.github.io/</id><title type="html">Rishab Ketan Doshi</title><subtitle>A Computer Engineer, Entrepreneur at heart. Passionate about solving problems.
</subtitle><author><name>Rishab Ketan Doshi</name><email>rishabketandoshi@gmail.com</email></author><entry><title type="html">Factfulness book summary</title><link href="https://rishabkdoshi.github.io/writes/2018/06/18/factfulness/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Factfulness book summary" /><published>2018-06-18T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2018-06-18T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>https://rishabkdoshi.github.io/writes/2018/06/18/factfulness</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://rishabkdoshi.github.io/writes/2018/06/18/factfulness/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/34890015-factfulness&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;https://images.gr-assets.com/books/1506097470l/34890015.jpg&quot; height=&quot;500&quot; width=&quot;300&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; width: 50%;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: justify;text-justify: inter-word;&quot;&gt;
This book was published just a few months after Hans Rosling passed away. An incredible read where Hans and team have beautifully provided a data-driven framework to look at the world and societies. He asks a fundamental set of questions on health care, disasters, environmental change, societal development etc. and asks the reader to guess the answers. He then proves that most audiences of the survey tend to select unoptimistic answers for all the questions. He then goes on to reveal the correct answers and then proposes a framework to look at the world. Through his life stories he demonstrates various instincts like urgency, fear etc., which make us feel unoptimistic/dejected about world conditions and then provides a factfull way of looking at the world. Highly recommended read.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some interesting highlights from the book:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;Every group of people I ask thinks the world is more frightening, more violent, and more hopeless—in short, more dramatic—than it really is.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;I decided to start doing more than just testing knowledge and exposing ignorance. I decided to try to understand why. Why was this ignorance about the world so widespread and so persistent?&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;Step-by-step, year-by-year, the world is improving. Not on every single measure every single year, but as a rule. Though the world faces huge challenges, we have made tremendous progress. This is the fact-based worldview.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;need to learn to control our drama intake. Uncontrolled, our appetite for the dramatic goes too far, prevents us from seeing the world as it is, and leads us terribly astray.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;Factfulness, like a healthy diet and regular exercise, can and should become part of your daily life.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;Misconceptions disappear only if there is some equally simple but more relevant way of thinking to replace them.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;Culture and freedom, the goals of development, can be hard to measure, but guitars per capita is a good proxy. And boy, has that improved.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;“Warning: Objects in Your Memories Were Worse Than They Appear&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;“possibilist.” That’s something I made up. It means someone who neither hopes without reason, nor fears without reason, someone who constantly resists the overdramatic worldview.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt; When we are afraid, we do not see clearly.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Rishab Ketan Doshi</name><email>rishabketandoshi@gmail.com</email></author><category term="book_summary" /><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://rishabkdoshi.github.io/assets/img/content/hit_refresh.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Hit Refresh book summary</title><link href="https://rishabkdoshi.github.io/writes/2018/06/01/hit-refresh/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hit Refresh book summary" /><published>2018-06-01T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2018-06-01T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>https://rishabkdoshi.github.io/writes/2018/06/01/hit-refresh</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://rishabkdoshi.github.io/writes/2018/06/01/hit-refresh/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/40720899-hit-refresh&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;https://images.gr-assets.com/books/1506565784l/30835567.jpg&quot; height=&quot;500&quot; width=&quot;300&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; width: 50%;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: justify;text-justify: inter-word;&quot;&gt;
Found this to be a very interesting book by Satya Nadella. He demonstrates how each of his life stages(schooling in India, love for cricket, parental experiences) have influenced his opinions and decisions he's made through the years at Microsoft. He then talks about the importance of culture in an organization, the struggles associated with bringing about a cultural transformation and then goes on to attribute the gains seen by Microsoft in recent years to its successful cultural transformation. He goes on to give his perspectives on technology's role in future societies specifically upcoming areas like Artificial Intelligence concluding by sharing his optimism about the future.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some interesting highlights from the book:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;Ideas excite me. Empathy grounds and centers me.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;If you could understand impermanence deeply, you would develop more equanimity. You would not get too excited about either the ups or downs of life.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;“the future enters into us, in order to transform itself in us, long before it happens.”&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;I said that I was honored, humbled, and excited. They were unplanned words, but they perfectly captured how I felt.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;you must always have respect for your competitor, but don’t be in awe. Go and compete.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;Steve Jobs understood what the soul of a company is. He once said that “design is the fundamental soul of a man-made creation that ends up expressing itself in successive outer layers of the product or service.”&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;“consistency is better than perfection.”&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;“At the end of the next year if we were tried in a court of law and the charge was that we failed to pursue our mission, would there be enough evidence to convict us?”&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;Trust is not only dependent on our technology but also the legal framework that governs it.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt; we want to build intelligence that augments human abilities and experiences. &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;computer pioneer Alan Kay quips, “The best way to predict the future is to invent it.” In the AI context, he’s basically saying, Stop predicting what the future will be like; instead, create it in a principled way.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;In software development terms, AI is becoming a third run time—the next system on top of which programmers will build and execute applications.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;∑ (Education + Innovation) x Intensity of Tech Use = Economic Growth&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;i&gt;“Business is humanity’s most resilient, iterative, and productive mechanism for creating change in the world.”&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Rishab Ketan Doshi</name><email>rishabketandoshi@gmail.com</email></author><category term="book_summary" /><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://rishabkdoshi.github.io/assets/img/content/hit_refresh.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Email Monitoring?</title><link href="https://rishabkdoshi.github.io/writes/2017/07/03/email-monitoring/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Email Monitoring?" /><published>2017-07-03T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2017-07-03T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>https://rishabkdoshi.github.io/writes/2017/07/03/email-monitoring</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://rishabkdoshi.github.io/writes/2017/07/03/email-monitoring/">&lt;p&gt;
&lt;b&gt;&lt;i&gt;Company management should conduct routine monitoring of all employee e-mail correspondence.  Such monitoring will reduce the waste of resources such as time and system capacity, as well as protect the company from lawsuits.
.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Write a response in which you discuss your views on the policy and explain your reasoning for the position you take. In developing and supporting your position, you should consider the possible consequences of implementing the policy and explain how these consequences shape your position.
&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The policy suggests that Company Management should conduct routine monitoring of all employee e-mail correspondence to reduce the waste of resources such as time and system capacity and also protecting the company from lawsuits. I partially disagree with this policy and feel that implementing such a policy may do more harm than good to the company. The concerns that this policy aims to solve can be solved in alternative ways, which are almost equally effective and will not create a sense of distrust amongst the employees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the major problems associated with this policy is that it will curb the free flow of thought amongst the employees in the company, the employees may get a feeling that someone is always watching them and they may not raise genuine queries, concerns that they have, fearing that this may hamper their growth within the company. For example: If a person X has attended a knowledge transfer session from another group of people in the company, and he/she has some follow up questions regarding the same. They may be hesitant to reach out to the people who conducted the session, as they may feel that the company management feels that these questions are redundant and feel that this person is actually asking extremely fundamental questions which are requisite to be known. This in turn affects his/her complete understanding of the topic and may hamper his/her ability to deliver the desired outcomes.
Another major problem associated with this policy is that it will create an environment of distrust amongst the employees of the company. If they have a feeling that somebody’s always monitoring the emails being sent out, it may lead them to think that the company doesn’t trust the employee to do the right thing. That the company views all employees as vicious people aiming to work in malevolent manners to create harm for the company. Though it may be true that there may be certain people who would have such malicious intents, distrusting the entire employee population to do such things will do more harm than good. Employees would stop raising genuine queries as pointed out earlier, further employees would not freely communicate and this may lead to a state of chaos where people refrain from saying things that they genuinely feel about the company policies, fearing that the management may read the same and possibly take dire actions against the people in question. This hampers genuine employee feedback which is vital for a company to grow. It is said that Seek Feedback, it is a gift, creating an environment which leads to loss of anonymity of feedback will just entirely hamper the feedback received, leading the company to be completely misguided about the employee morale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The policy is being implemented to ensure that there is a judicious use of system and time resources that are at the company’s disposal and to protect the company from lawsuits. It also says that the monitoring will be done by the company management. The company management is not necessarily involved at the granular level contextual details of the problems that the teams are working to solve, what the management may deem as unnecessary based on their facile understanding may actually be essential to the functioning of the team. So for the effective implementation of this policy it is important that the people monitoring the email correspondence are cognisant of what is important and unimportant to the effective functioning of the team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problems that the policy attempts to address can be taken up in alternative ways without hampering the employee morale and the creating a sense of distrust in the company’s ecosystem.
To ensure that the company’s resources such as system capacity and time are not wasted. The company’s mail servers can specify a threshold size of an email in bytes, which the senders cannot exceed. This would ensure that people would communicate freely and also bridle them from abusing the resources at their disposal. To protect the company from lawsuits, the company can monitor all the email correspondence that goes out of the company’s mail network. This would ensure that no confidential company data is compromised, and in case of compromise it will enable the company to identify the miscreant.
As can be seen above, there are lot of repercussions that come with implementing this policy and the problems that the policy aims to solve can be achieved via other methods. So it is best to keep the best interests of the employee in mind.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Rishab Ketan Doshi</name><email>rishabketandoshi@gmail.com</email></author><category term="gre_awa_analyze_issue" /><summary type="html">Company management should conduct routine monitoring of all employee e-mail correspondence. Such monitoring will reduce the waste of resources such as time and system capacity, as well as protect the company from lawsuits. . Write a response in which you discuss your views on the policy and explain your reasoning for the position you take. In developing and supporting your position, you should consider the possible consequences of implementing the policy and explain how these consequences shape your position.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://rishabkdoshi.github.io/assets/img/default.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Arts or Military??</title><link href="https://rishabkdoshi.github.io/writes/2017/07/01/arts-vs-military/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Arts or Military??" /><published>2017-07-01T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2017-07-01T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>https://rishabkdoshi.github.io/writes/2017/07/01/arts-vs-military</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://rishabkdoshi.github.io/writes/2017/07/01/arts-vs-military/">&lt;p&gt;
&lt;b&gt;&lt;i&gt;Governments should invest as much in the arts as they do in the military.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Write a response in which you discuss the extent to which you agree or disagree with the recommendation and explain your reasoning for the position you take. In developing and supporting your position, describe specific circumstances in which adopting the recommendation would or would not be advantageous and explain how these examples shape your position.
&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The recommendation is that Governments should invest as much in art as they do in military. I partially disagree with this recommendation. It is true that governments should invest sufficient amounts in art, but making it comparable to the military spending of the country would be unwise in this current era where terrorism is widespread and prevalent across boundaries of countries. In a chimerical situation wherein all countries have completely and wholly abandoned war, and there are zero terrorist groups and organisations then Governments may even not need to have a significant military budget, and could consider investing in art more than their military spending. But with the situation that is prevalent today it would be imprudent for the governments to completely adopt this recommendation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is important to analyse the role that the military places in every country. The military is responsible for defending the sovereignty of the country and its citizens in case of wartimes. In case of natural disasters the military is pressed into relief operations. For example: During the Tsunami wave in 2004 in Chennai,India. The military conducted relief operations over weeks to ensure that people are able to come back to their normal lives. They persevered along with numerous other organisations to ensure that no epidemics break out and people are taken care of.  Further to this the military takes care of various other responsibilities that are fundamental to the well being of a nation and all its inhabitants. Given that the military is responsible of such fundamental duties, that are required by the nation. It is only wise that the Government which is responsible for the governance of the nation, aptly fund the military and ensure that the military personnel are not left wanting for anything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also most of the countries today have non-coterminous boundaries, with difficult conditions at various borders of the country. If the military doesn’t have a strong presence at each of the borders, the country is susceptible to attacks which may harm the citizens and artists inhabiting the country. For example: India’s border with China at Tawang is at altitudes of over 15000ft above sea level. At such conditions it is extremely difficult for the military personnel. With low amounts of oxygen in the air, extreme temperatures and poor connectivity to major nearby towns. They have to navigate through rough conditions for basic necessities. In such conditions it is necessary for the government to set up small self sustainable military camps at the border locations to ensure that the military is able to defend the border. In order to do so, the government needs to spend significant amounts of money for the military.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is also important to realise that the costs of weapons, artillery etc. that are required by the military  is significantly much more than that of the goods that are required for most art forms. In such cases a country can do without spending too much on art, but without investing in the latest military technologies, a country would be ill-prepared when it faces an attack from opponents who posses much superior weapons. For example: In 19th century India, there were numerous Kingdoms that were coming up and the Mughal empire known for its erstwhile military superiority was continuously losing the areas under its kingdom. The then Mughal leader Bahadur Shah Zafar hadn’t made adequate investments in upgrading their military capabilities and the people faced grave atrocities after their lands were captured. This is a classic example as to why it is important to continually invest in upgrading the military capabilities of the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It may argued that the arts and culture of a country are a primary identity of the country and it is important to make investments to preserve and enrich the arts, cultures and traditions of the country. I completely agree with this, but the spending required for fields as diverse as Military and Arts is not comparable. And underfunding the military to preserve the arts would be imprudent, because if the military is not equipped to defend the country in case of attacks, the very art and culture forms that the government sought to preserve are threatened to be expunged by enemy forces in wartime. This would lead to both loss of territory and a loss of arts and culture.
So it is necessary to take a balanced approach to providing adequate funding to the military that is fundamental to the existence of every country.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Rishab Ketan Doshi</name><email>rishabketandoshi@gmail.com</email></author><category term="gre_awa_analyze_issue" /><summary type="html">Governments should invest as much in the arts as they do in the military. Write a response in which you discuss the extent to which you agree or disagree with the recommendation and explain your reasoning for the position you take. In developing and supporting your position, describe specific circumstances in which adopting the recommendation would or would not be advantageous and explain how these examples shape your position.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://rishabkdoshi.github.io/assets/img/default.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Internet Good or Bad?</title><link href="https://rishabkdoshi.github.io/writes/2017/06/17/internet-affects-attention-span/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Internet Good or Bad?" /><published>2017-06-17T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2017-06-17T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>https://rishabkdoshi.github.io/writes/2017/06/17/internet-affects-attention-span</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://rishabkdoshi.github.io/writes/2017/06/17/internet-affects-attention-span/">&lt;p&gt;
&lt;b&gt;&lt;i&gt;Mass media and the internet have caused people’s attention spans to get shorter. However, the overall effect has been positive: while people are less able  to focus on one thing, they more than make up for it with an enhanced ability to sort through large quantities of information and find what’s important.
.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Write a response in which you discuss the extent to which you agree or disagree with the claim. In developing and supporting your position, be sure to address the most compelling reasons or examples that could be used to challenge your position.
&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The claim states that the Mass media and Internet have caused people’s attention span to get shorter, at the same time this has had an overall positive effect as people have developed an enhanced ability to sort through large quantities of information and incisively understand what’s important and what’s extraneous. I agree with this claim and there are a multitude of reasons as to how this claim can be justified as elucidated below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is definitely true that there has been an exponential growth in the amount of content that is available in terms of digital and mass media, which has been primarily accelerated due to the increasing accessibility to the internet. We have more than a billion users on Facebook a social network, logging in everyday sharing stories of their daily lives, videos of their interests and creating groups of like minded people. We have got twitter, a micro-blogging platform which again has hundreds of millions of users using the platform to follow the people they are interested in knowing about. We also have all the major news and media organisations creating an online presence on these platforms and their own websites, further youtube is a video sharing platform on which one billion hours of video is watched by masses across geographies on an everyday basis. We have email systems, which people use for varied reasons ranging from official tp personal purposes. So it can’t be contested that there is a plethora information available on the mass media. Now as the claim states it is easy for people to get overwhelmed by this myriad of information available to them, hence not being able to have appreciable attention spans. But it is important to note that by using these platforms over a period of time, people learn to wade through larger quantities of information than they ever used to before and develop an ability to filter out what is important and what is not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example: Each of the social media platforms allow the user to tailor what appears on their feed, if the user feels that a particular source of information is garbage/extraneous and the user doesn’t really benefit from that source. The user can choose to unfollow that source. So as can be seen with time the user learns to filter out sources which are not beneficial to him/her.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further the news sources that the user uses to keep up-to-date may have a lot of extraneous information which may not necessarily be of interest to the user, in order to keep the user engaged the news and media websites have developed the technological capabilites to understand what the user really is interested in and filter out what is of interest to him, so as can be seen not only has this led to an improvement in the ability of the user to sort through large quantities of information, it has also resulted in an improvement in technology of how to push most relevant information to each individual user, engendering a completely personal experience. Further there are aggregation platforms like Google News, which aggregate news data from various news sources and tailors it for every user. If an Indian visits Google News, he/she gets the most relevant news based on the geography.
Similarly in social media networks like Facebook, Twitter there is a trending feature which informs the user about the post or article that is most prevailing and what people are finding compelling at the current time. This is identified by metrics which empowers people to up vote or down vote a particular post that they come across in their feed, so it gives the power to users to decide if this piece of information is relevant or irrelevant or is spam.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further there has been a great improvement in a technology called as the Search Engines. These are basically websites which a user visits in order to find a particular piece of information, these search engines crawl through the internet and rank websites based on content, so when a user queries for &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Quantum Physics&lt;/code&gt; the Search Engine is able to pull out the most highly rated articles on the topic and user gets what he/she is looking for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It may be argued that the user could continually get interrupted by ending up landing on the varied platforms mentioned above and actually have a shortened attention span. For example: If a user finds an article on &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Quantum Physics&lt;/code&gt; on a particular website and shares it on a social media platform, he/she may start watching some other irrelevant content like some movie videos etc. Or if the user is studying and he gets notified that his friend has shared some compelling content on Facebook, he may end up losing his attention span. This is definitely possible and can occur, however to tackle these problems there are tools available that let you block out notifications for a period of time, so a user can decide to block out notifications, there are also tools available that let users block out particular websites for a period of time. There are also productivity tools available that define metrics about where the user spends his/her time.These can be used by the user to tackle the attention span issue.
As can be seen, that the mass media has definitely empowered the users, but also given them the added responsibility of ensuring that they don’t get lost in these websites.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Rishab Ketan Doshi</name><email>rishabketandoshi@gmail.com</email></author><category term="gre_awa_analyze_issue" /><summary type="html">Mass media and the internet have caused people’s attention spans to get shorter. However, the overall effect has been positive: while people are less able to focus on one thing, they more than make up for it with an enhanced ability to sort through large quantities of information and find what’s important. . Write a response in which you discuss the extent to which you agree or disagree with the claim. In developing and supporting your position, be sure to address the most compelling reasons or examples that could be used to challenge your position.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://rishabkdoshi.github.io/assets/img/default.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Educations primary motive?</title><link href="https://rishabkdoshi.github.io/writes/2017/06/12/educations-motive-what/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Educations primary motive?" /><published>2017-06-12T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2017-06-12T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>https://rishabkdoshi.github.io/writes/2017/06/12/educations-motive-what</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://rishabkdoshi.github.io/writes/2017/06/12/educations-motive-what/">&lt;p&gt;
&lt;b&gt;&lt;i&gt;Some people believe that teaching morality should be the foundation of education. Others believe that teaching a foundation of logical reasoning would do more to produce a moral society.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Write a response in which you discuss which view  more closely aligns with your own position and explain your reasoning for the position you take. In developing and supporting your position, you should address both of the views presented above.
&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The view states that there are two different opinions as to what should be the foundation of education in order to produce a more moral society. Some people believe that teaching morality should be the foundation of education, while others believe that teaching a foundation of logical reasoning would do more to produce a moral society. As we are discussing the foundation of education which is one of the most vital tools that equips humanity to progress with time, it is necessary to take a balanced approach to this view. I feel that in order to build a more moral and inclusive society it is important to have morality as a foundation for education, but singular focus on morality wouldn’t suffice and this foundation built on morals is to be strengthened by teaching of logical reasoning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is important that humans are moral in nature and that there is mutual co-operation between people that come from different walks of life, only this will ensure a halcyon atmosphere conducive for all of humanity to continue prospering.
If people are not taught moral values and their foundation is only based on logical reasoning, we may be faced with a situation wherein we have an extremely smart person who doesn’t have moral values and is not compassionate about fellow human beings coming up with a scheme that may put majority of humanity at stake. For example: If a really smart person X having had an education based purely on logical reasoning without any emphasis on morals comes up with a scheme to force isolation of old people, based on his logic that these are old people and don’t really contribute anymore to humanity and are just consuming valuable resources, it will end up affecting a large part of the population. What this person may not realise is that these fellow human beings who may logically not help in everyday activities, have toiled hard over the years and this is the time for them to relaxe, more importantly these people have valuable first hand  experience of various situations which is much greater than bookish logical knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also if logical reasoning is the sole foundation of education, we may be faced with a situation wherein an entire community or an entire nation is completely oppressed due to lack of economic and social development. For example: A leader of developed country who has had an education solely based on logical reasoning may stop aiding other developing countries citing unjustified costs , but what this leader may not realise is that by aiding developing countries he/she’s aiding humanity as a whole to progress, which is extremely valuable especially in the long run as these citizens from developing countries will also contribute to growth and this joint effort from people across countries , races , geographies will propel humanity forward. It will bring in diverse opinions which may not have been the case if all the leaders of the world are from a select few countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The importance of morality being a foundation of education has been illustrated above, however it is important to note that morality has to be strongly complemented by logical reasoning in education. This is necessary because irrespective of how moral a person is, he/she needs to be equipped to take logical decisions. A moral person may be extremely inclusive, but without having critical thinking and logical reasoning capabilities he/she may not be able to act during grave situations and his/her morality and compassion for other human beings wouldn’t serve him/her any good in such situations. For example: A leader who has had an education solely based on morals is faced with a situation wherein people in his/her community are falling sick because of a deadly contagious disease, this leader should have the necessary logical reasoning capability to isolate these infected people into a separate area and provide treatment to them there. Had the person not had these logical thinking skills, he/she may not act and the entire community will be affected.
So it is clear that the morality should be at the foundation of education, however morality has to be closely complemented with logical reasoning to strengthen this foundation. After all we are stronger together.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Rishab Ketan Doshi</name><email>rishabketandoshi@gmail.com</email></author><category term="gre_awa_analyze_issue" /><summary type="html">Some people believe that teaching morality should be the foundation of education. Others believe that teaching a foundation of logical reasoning would do more to produce a moral society. Write a response in which you discuss which view more closely aligns with your own position and explain your reasoning for the position you take. In developing and supporting your position, you should address both of the views presented above.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://rishabkdoshi.github.io/assets/img/default.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Individual dreams vs Enforced Goals??</title><link href="https://rishabkdoshi.github.io/writes/2017/06/09/dreams-vs-enforced-goals/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Individual dreams vs Enforced Goals??" /><published>2017-06-09T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2017-06-09T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>https://rishabkdoshi.github.io/writes/2017/06/09/dreams-vs-enforced-goals</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://rishabkdoshi.github.io/writes/2017/06/09/dreams-vs-enforced-goals/">&lt;p&gt;
&lt;b&gt;&lt;i&gt;Claim:  Even though young people often receive the advice to “follow your dreams,” more emphasis should be placed on picking worthy goals.

Reason:  Many people’s dreams are inherently selfish.
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Write a response in which you discuss the extent to which you agree or disagree with the claim AND the reason on which that claim is based.
&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The claim states that even though young people are often advised to ‘follow their dreams’, there should be a greater emphasis on picking worthy goals. The reason stated is that many people’s dreams are selfish. The reasoning may seem valid, but I partially disagree with the claim as it restricts the younger generation of people to have goals that are considered worthy in the general society, which will eventually result in a glut of people following very similar dreams and hence restrict the progress.
Firstly when an emphasis on placed on picking worthy goals instead of following your dreams we are restricting the younger people from thinking out of the box, thereby restricting innovation. This will hence lead to a stagnation of progress that humans make. For example: In the 18th century one of the worthy goals was to be a member in the Royal Court, had everyone in 18th century been a member in the royal court we wouldn’t have seen the progress we have today. Had Thomas Edison not relentlessly pursued his dream of inventing the Tubelight, we might not have had tube lights. His passion for ensuring success of his dream, has resulted in making people’s lives so easy that todays generation don’t imagine a world without lights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another important point to consider is that humans as a race have evolved into a composition of set of diverse and extremely different people. Everyone has different thoughts and ideas and we are not primitive beings like ants or rodents who are only concerned with extremely cardinal aspects of life like mating and food consumption. This evolution has empowered us to be different, and we should respect this aspect and nurture the younger generation to build on top of our achievements, make further progress than what has been possible in the previous generations. The worthy goals have to be set by the younger generation, worthy goals can be set by following one’s dreams as well. For example: If a person who was extremely passionate about singing is exhorted to take up engineering may end up as a mediocre engineer, had the person been given the freedom to choose his/her area and follow the dreams, we might have had an excellent singer. Emphasis should be laid on pursuit of excellence in the chosen field not on pursuit of goals viewed as worthy by the society in general.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reasoning given states that many people are selfish and the dreams they choose maybe selfish and may not benefit the entire humanity. However it is important to note that any success which is achieved by an individual is not restricted to the individual is not necessarily restricted to the individual itself, it could be extended to help the society in general. Even if the success it can’t be replicated across the world, it will serve as an inspiration to other people to take up solving the problem given that it has successfully been solved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further todays younger people are tomorrows citizens and they should learn to take important and difficult decisions, if following their dreams leads to a failure the younger people should be able to introspect and understand why something failed. They should be encouraged to possess critical skills to ensure that they don’t repeat their mistakes. After all failure is a great teacher. Had our ancestors been coaxed to pursue worthy goals, they wouldn’t have tried out a variety of fields, we might have still been a primitive savage race, only concerned about hunting and procreation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is clear that restricting people to pursue goals viewed as worthy by the society in general is harmful to the progress humans make as a race, however it is important that emphasis is laid on becoming the paragon in the chosen fields. Further to tackle the problem of the inventions being restricted to a select few, we have to encourage and ensure that requisite information is available to all about the invention. The web is a powerful medium that has already enabled this.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Rishab Ketan Doshi</name><email>rishabketandoshi@gmail.com</email></author><category term="gre_awa_analyze_issue" /><summary type="html">Claim: Even though young people often receive the advice to “follow your dreams,” more emphasis should be placed on picking worthy goals.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://rishabkdoshi.github.io/assets/img/default.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Are emotional decision makers bad?</title><link href="https://rishabkdoshi.github.io/writes/2017/05/20/emotional-decision-makers-bad/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Are emotional decision makers bad?" /><published>2017-05-20T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2017-05-20T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>https://rishabkdoshi.github.io/writes/2017/05/20/emotional-decision-makers-bad</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://rishabkdoshi.github.io/writes/2017/05/20/emotional-decision-makers-bad/">&lt;p&gt;
&lt;b&gt;&lt;i&gt;People who make decisions based on emotion and justify those decisions with logic afterwards are poor decision makers.
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Write a response in which you discuss the extent to which you agree or disagree with the statement and explain your reasoning for the position you take. In developing and supporting your position, you should consider ways in which the statement might or might not hold true and explain how these considerations shape your position.
&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The statement says that people who take decisions based on emotions and later justify these decisions logically are poor decision makers. I feel that this statement is too extreme in its treatment of people who take decisions based on emotions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firstly, it is important to note that not all decisions taken based on emotions turn out to be bad decisions. For example: If a person is at an inflection point at his/her career, and in order to get that next promotion he/she needs to move from New York to California. At the same time he/she is responsible for the well being of his/her parents, younger siblings. In such cases if the person decides not to take the promotion in order to take care of his/her dependents. This decision may appear to others as an impractical decision driven by emotions, however this is a necessary decision when viewed from the eyes of the decision maker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further it is important be cognizant of the fact that people take a lot of decisions on an everyday basis and all decisions are not of the same importance or have the same magnitude. So judging a person as a poor decision maker just based on the fact that he/she is making few decisions driven by emotions would be illogical. For example: If a person started the day on a bad note and makes a poor dressing choice, this decision was affected by the persons emotions at the point of making the decision, but labelling the person as a poor decision maker just by a trivial decision like poor dressing is flawed. The same person could be very decisive in terms of where his/her investments should be made and might even have extremely clear life goals. If the person is capable of making such byzantine decisions, it would be imprudent to label him/her as a poor decision maker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time if a person makes a poor decision which is not as trivial and has dire consequences, if the person is justifying the poor decision made, it is an indication that the person is trying to bring forth a point of view which is not very obvious but made sense to the decision maker at the point of time of making the decision. The decision maker trying to justify the decision is also representative of the fact that the person is willing to be accountable for the decisions he/she has made and wants to take everyone into confidence about a possible lapse of judgement. For example: If a football team A is playing a game and it is the last game for player X, if the coach decides to give player X a chance to play despite X not being in the greatest of form. This decision is based on an emotion. If team A ends up losing it will appear as a rash decision by the coach to let player X take on the field. However the coach justifies this decision saying that the team A had already qualified for the playoffs and it didn’t hurt to let player X take the field, considering that X had contributed so much to the team. This decision which initially appears rash doesn’t really turn out to be rash on closer inspection.
So it can be clearly seen that not all decisions that are taken are of equal importance, some that are driven by emotions may turn out to be bad, but if logically justified it may bring out views that may not have been anticipated.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Rishab Ketan Doshi</name><email>rishabketandoshi@gmail.com</email></author><category term="gre_awa_analyze_issue" /><summary type="html">People who make decisions based on emotion and justify those decisions with logic afterwards are poor decision makers. Write a response in which you discuss the extent to which you agree or disagree with the statement and explain your reasoning for the position you take. In developing and supporting your position, you should consider ways in which the statement might or might not hold true and explain how these considerations shape your position.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://rishabkdoshi.github.io/assets/img/default.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Cloud computing as I understand it!</title><link href="https://rishabkdoshi.github.io/writes/2016/08/08/cloud-computing/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cloud computing as I understand it!" /><published>2016-08-08T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2016-08-08T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>https://rishabkdoshi.github.io/writes/2016/08/08/cloud-computing</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://rishabkdoshi.github.io/writes/2016/08/08/cloud-computing/">&lt;p&gt;I’m sure most of us have heard this fancy term thrown around by a lot of tech geeks these days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what is cloud computing?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have attempted to explain the concept by drawing some similar real world analogies in this article.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just like electrical appliances need electricity to run, computer software needs some sort of a fuel to run on. In this case the fuel is the hardware that the software is deployed on. In olden days the electricity or the fuel required to perform simple domestic jobs like heating water, cooking etc. was sourced using energy created at home either by burning firewood or having a dedicated power grid installed to serve the domestic needs. Similarly the hardware required to run the software that we use was initially sourced locally by having data centres that house servers running the required software and with cloud computing they are being sourced from analogous hardware grids as a service. This service is provided by Cloud service providers(CSP’s). A CSP is analogous to the electricity board that generates and distributes power to our homes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now there are certain analogies that we can draw from the above comparison, just like how we only want to be concerned about the availability of the electricity supply and are not bothered about how the electricity is generated, we don’t want to be concerned about maintaining hardware to run software.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us think about what would happen if we had a small function at home and correspondingly we have a spike in the electricity consumption . If we were dependent on locally creating the required energy, we would have to have the infrastructure capable of generating the maximum energy we need. This infrastructure would become obsolete after the function is over, and the initial overhead costs involved in setting up the infrastructure would not be justified only for a temporary spike in electricity consumption.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So how have we been solving this issue ?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We draw electricity from a grid which supplies electricity from a power house and has the infrastructure in place to serve multiple customers based on demand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we don’t have to worry about setting up additional infrastructure to serve the consumption and maximise our involvement in making other arrangements for the party.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly in the software world , there are multiple occasions when companies will have a huge spike in usage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example an e-commerce company like Walmart will have a large rush of customers visiting the website and using the mobile apps on Black Friday sale days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Flipkart and Myntra will have a huge spike in users during the Diwali sales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So traditionally these companies would set up the infrastructure to serve the usage spike. This infrastructure would lie idle on regular days. Now with the shift to the cloud, all that Flipkart or Walmart have to do is deploy the application on the Cloud and the application would scale as the users spike, creating multiple instances of the software application on new hardware based on demand. This is again analogous to the electricity grid where you can draw as much electricity as you need from the grid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So cloud computing solved a very important problem faced by many companies that is scalability, and it did so by simply making the fuel required to run the software available as a simple service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also now that the service was available on demand, we no longer need the expensive infrastructure required to maintain the up time of the application during peak hours.This is also good because this same infrastructure would be idle at regular loads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So this brought in an elastic feature wherein there was as much fuel as required by the application, since it was sourced from the grid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not too much when there was low usage and not too little when there was high usage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just like in our function at home situation, where we could focus on making the arrangements for the function instead of diverting our energy on creating the energy required, Cloud gave Software companies the freedom to focus on core product, business development and simplified the infrastructure creation and maintenance .&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also gave software companies the freedom to experiment on new ideas by creating the software application on the cloud and testing the hypothesis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If it worked, great. Since the software is hosted on cloud it can scale. If it didn’t meet expectations, not a problem as the company didn’t acquire expensive hardware specifically to run this experiment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is also one of the major reasons we see so many web based startups coming up. In fact Software startups are considered to be ready for VC funding if they have a solid IT infrastructure setup and with the coming up of Cloud Computing services offered by CSP’s this can be easily taken care of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So as we can clearly see,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cloud computing has a lot of pros few of which have been discussed in this article and like with everything in this world it has its set of cons as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We shall discuss them in detail in another article.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt; Originally published &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@rishabketandoshi/cloud-computing-as-i-understand-it-466b4445b68a&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Rishab Ketan Doshi</name><email>rishabketandoshi@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html">I’m sure most of us have heard this fancy term thrown around by a lot of tech geeks these days.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://rishabkdoshi.github.io/assets/img/default.jpg" /></entry></feed>